<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="exception-handling" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Exception handling</title>

  <toc/>

  <section id="exception-handling:why">
    <title>Why not just use try and catch?</title>

    <para>Most exceptions that are thrown are unexpected: we don't expect them to happen (especially during production)
      such as:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <literal>NullPointerException</literal>: Didn't I double checked all my source code to avoid NPE's?
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <literal>CvsParserException</literal>: Why did the user pick a html file when I asked him for a CVS file?
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <literal>IDidNotKnowThisExistedRuntimeException</literal>: What the ...?
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>And if you except some of them, you ussually can't really fix the problem, just deal with it:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Log the exception.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Notify the user that whatever he tried didn't work, preferably with an not-technical, exception-specific
          explanation.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Either shutdown the application or allow the user to continue (and try again).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>You could use try-catch during every user action:</para>

    <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[protected boolean onFinish() {
    try {
        form.getFormModel().commit();
    // ...
    getApplicationContext().publishEvent(new LifecycleApplicationEvent(eventType, getEditingContact()));
    return true;
    } catch (Throwable throwable) {
        handleException(throwable);
    }
}]]></programlisting>

    <para>But this is tedious and error prone:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>It's easy to forget to try catch some code, which makes the exception escape to the top layer exception
          handler.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>You could unwillingly eat the exception, not logging it:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>If you handle an exception, but forget to log it and/or show it to the user.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>If you throw an exception in the catch or finally part, only the last exception bubbles up,
              effectively hiding the real exception.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>In production, this leads to discussions where the user is sure
          he pushed the button (which he did in this case) and the programmer is
          sure the user didn't because the system didn't report anything and
          nothing has changed. If you notice that while you are fixing a issue,
          an exception is eaten (making it hard to identify the original issue),
          create a new issue because exceptions are eaten and fix that
          first.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You are in danger to handle the same exception on 2 different
          layers, effectively logging it or notifing the user twice.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>In some layers or parts of the application, it might not be
          clear if you need to notify the user (and which user) through a swing
          dialog or JSP or webservice response.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Valkyrie's exception handling system uses the top layer
      exception handling. It expects that all other layers let the exception
      bubble up.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="exception-handling:builtin">
    <title>Built-in exception handlers</title>

    <para>The standard exception handler in Valkyrie is a simple delegating handler which delegates exception handling
        for all exception types to a handler that shows a <classname>JXErrorDialog</classname>.
    </para>

    <para>However, you can use any of the following built-in handlers:</para>

    <section>
      <title>SilentExceptionHandler</title>

      <para>Logs a throwable on an error level but does not notify the user in any way. Normally
        it is a bad practice not to notify the user if something goes
        wrong.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>MessagesDialogExceptionHandler</title>

      <para>Shows the exception in a dialog to the user (as well as logging
        it). You can set a log level and the icon of the dialog depends on that
        log level. The shown dialog has a caption (= dialog title) and
        description (= dialog content), which are fetched from the i18n messages
        files. There are 2 ways to resolve those messages: static or dynamic
        (default).
      </para>

      <para>You can statically set the title and description by setting the
        <literal>messagesKey</literal>
        property. However, it's a lot more
        powerfull to use the default dynamic behaviour based on the class of the
        exception. For example if a
        <literal>NumberFormatException</literal>
        is
        thrown, it will first look for these i18n keys:
      </para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[java.lang.NumberFormatException.caption=Not a number
java.lang.NumberFormatException.description=You did not enter a a valid number.\nPlease enter a valid number.]]></programlisting>

      <para>If these messages keys don't exist, it will fall back to the
        parent class of<literal>NumberFormatException</literal>, which is
        <literal>IllegalArgumentException</literal>:
      </para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[java.lang.IllegalArgumentException.caption=...
java.lang.IllegalArgumentException.description=...]]></programlisting>

      <para>It will continue to fall back up the chain, untill it reaches
        <literal>Throwable</literal>. This allows you to direct all unexpected
        exceptions (for example
        <literal>IDidNotKnowThisExistedRuntimeException</literal>) to a
        <literal>MessagesDialogExceptionHandler</literal>
        that logs them as an
        error and shows a generic message. You can even use
        <literal>{0}</literal>
        in your i18n message to show the
        <literal>exception.getMessage()</literal>
        in the description:
      </para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[# Double quotes(") need to be escaped (\"), single quotes (') always seem to break the replacing
of {0}.
java.lang.RuntimeException.caption = Unexpected general bug
java.lang.RuntimeException.description = \
The application experienced an unexpected bug,\n\
due to a programming error.\n\
\n\
The application is possibly in an inconsistent state.\n\
It is recommended to reboot the application.\n\
\n\
The exact bug is:\n\
{0}\n\
\n\
Please report this bug.

java.lang.Error.caption = Unexpected serious system failure
java.lang.Error.description = \
A serious system failure occured.\n\
\n\
The application is possibly in an inconsistent state.\n\
Reboot the application.\n\
\n\
The exact bug is:\n\
{0}\n\
\n\
Please report this bug.]]></programlisting>

      <para>Note that, although this dynamic system is pretty powerfull and
        avoids a lot of boilerplate, it's usually not a replacement for
        <literal>DelegatingExceptionHandler</literal>, because it doesn't allow
        you to assign different log levels, etc.
      </para>

      <para>You can set a shutdown policy on a dialog exception
        handler:
      </para>

     <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[handler.setShutdownPolicy(ShutdownPolicy.ASK);]]></programlisting>

      <para>This allows you to optionally enforce or propose a
        <literal>System.exit(1)</literal>.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>HibernateValidatorDialogExceptionHandler</title>

      <para>A special exception handler which can only handle an
        <literal>InvalidStateException</literal>
        thrown by Hibernate validator.
        It shows the failed validations to a user in a list in a dialog. In most
        cases it's inferiour to the
        <literal>HibernateRulesValidator</literal>
        which validates before the user presses the commit button. But because
        the latter forces you to hand code<literal>@AssertTrue</literal>'s and
        it could be working on stale client-side data, it's actually a very nice
        backup to also configure this exception handler as a delegate when encountering an <classname>InvalidStateException</classname>.
      </para>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Custom exception handler</title>

      <para>You can also extend
        <literal>AbstractLoggingExceptionHandler</literal>
        and implement this
        method:
      </para>

        <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public void notifyUserAboutException(Thread thread, Throwable throwable) {
    // ...
}]]></programlisting>

    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Picking the right exception handler for the right exception</title>

    <para>There are bunch of build-in exception handlers, but ussually there
      isn't one exception handler that fits alls exceptions. A
      <literal>DelegatingExceptionHandler</literal>
      allows you to delegate an
      exception to the right exception handler. It accepts a delegate list and
      traverses that list in order. The first delegate that can handle the
      exception, has to handle the exception and the rest of the delegate list
      is ignored.
    </para>

    <para>For example, here we configure authentication and authorization
      exceptions to a WARN<literal>MessagesDialogExceptionHandler</literal>,
      hibernate validator exceptions to an INFO
      <literal>HibernateValidatorDialogExceptionHandler</literal>
      and the rest
      to an ERROR<literal>MessagesDialogExceptionHandler</literal>.
    </para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../codesamples/exception-handling/xml/sample5.xml" parse="text"/></programlisting>

    <section>
      <title>SimpleExceptionHandlerDelegate</title>

      <para>Processes the exception if it is an instance of throwableClass or
        the throwableClassList.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>ChainInspectingExceptionHandlerDelegate</title>

      <para>In most cases this class is overkill and
        SimpleExceptionHandlerDelegate with a purger will suffice. However if
        those don't suffice, read the javadoc of this class.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>ExceptionPurger</title>

      <para>An exception purger allows you to cream off wrapper exceptions.
        This allows you to handle a chained exception in the chain of the
        uncaught exception, instead of the uncaught exception itself. Almost all
        exception handlers and delegate's support the use of a purger.
        <literal>DefaultExceptionPurger</literal>
        supports 2 ways to identify
        the depth to cream off: include or exclude based.
      </para>

      <para>A chained exception of the type in the
        <literal>includeThrowableClassList</literal>
        is stripped from all it's
        wrapper exceptions and handled by the exception handler or evaluated by
        the delegate. For example, we want to handle every
        <literal>MySQLIntegrityConstraintViolationException</literal>
        even if
        it's wrapped:
      </para>

      <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../codesamples/exception-handling/xml/sample6.xml" parse="text"/></programlisting>

      <para>A chained exception of the type in the
        <literal>excludeThrowableClassList</literal>
        is stripped together with
        all it's wrapper exceptions and it's cause is handled by the exception
        handler or evaluated by the delegate. For example the server wraps all
        exceptions in an annoying, useless
        <literal>WrappingServiceCallException</literal>
        and we want to get rid
        of it:
      </para>

      <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="../codesamples/exception-handling/xml/sample7.xml" parse="text"/></programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
