<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="integration"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:schemaLocation="
                http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
                http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd">
  <title>Integration with other frameworks</title>

  <toc/>
  
  <section id="integration:flexibility">
    <title>Flexibility</title>
    <para>
      Valkyrie, being a framework, provides the flexibility to add support for other Swing frameworks. This
      way, the standard toolkit can be enriched with all sorts of open-source, closed-source or even proprietary
      components.
    </para>
    <para>
      We’ll take a quick look at the current integrations for Valkyrie.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="integration:vldocking">
    <title>VLDocking</title>
    <para>
      VLDocking is a set of Java components that helps the Swing developer to build applications with docking
      capabilities, and even leverage existing applications to higher standards.
    </para>
    <para>
      Valkyrie provides an integration for this docking framework out-of-the-box. Examples on this integration
      are available in the samples included in Valkyrie.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="integration:jide">
    <title>JIDE</title>
    <para>
      JIDE provides a lot of Swing components that add a plethora of functionalities to the standard Swing toolkit. JIDE has both commercial as open-source components, so the possibilities for integrations are vast.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="integration:other">
    <title>Adding support for other frameworks</title>
    <para>
      Support for other Swing libraries can come in different sizes:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Other docking frameworks
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          MDI frameworks
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Input controls to create binders and bindings with
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Form frameworks
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Valkyrie is meant to be extended, so we’re sure some integrations are still to pop up.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>